<P>ENVIRONMENTAL ASSESSMENT
 </P>
<Part><P>May 2002
 </P>
<P>Abbreviations and Acronyms
 </P>
<P>ADFG	 Alaska Department of Fish and Game
 </P>
<P>ANO	 Alaska Native organization
 
Cook Inlet 
</P>
<P>CIMMC	 Cook Inlet Marine Mammal Council
 </P>
<P>ESA	 Endangered Species Act, as amended
 </P>
<P>MMPA 	 Marine Mammal Protection Act
 </P>
<P>NEPA	 National Environmental Policy Act
 </P>
<P>NMFS	 National Marine Fisheries Service
 </P>
<P>NOAA	 National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration
 </P>
<P>OSP	 Optimum Sustainable Population
 </P>
<P>RFA	 Regulatory Flexibility Act
 </P>
<P>SUMMARY
 </P>
<Sect><P>The National Marine Fisheries Service (NMFS) is entering into an

agreement with the Cook Inlet Marine Mammal Council (CIMMC) for

the cooperative management of the Cook Inlet (CI) beluga whales

under section 119 of the Marine Mammal Protection Act (MMPA) and

Public Law 106-553 for the year 2002. The co-management

agreement specifies the conditions under which a subsistence

harvest on CI beluga whales could be undertaken during the year

2002. The agreement specifies a harvest level of up to two (2)

whale strikes.
 </P>
<P>Abundance estimates for the CI beluga whale stock indicated a

decline of nearly 50 percent between 1994 and 1998, which caused

NMFS to designate the stock as depleted under the MMPA. Federal
 
authority to enter into the co-management agreement for the year

2002 derives from Public Law 106-553, which prohibits the hunting

of CI beluga whales except pursuant to a cooperative agreement

between NMFS and Alaska Native organizations (ANOs); and Section

119 of the MMPA which allows the Secretary to enter into

cooperative agreements with ANOs to conserve marine mammals and

provide co-management of subsistence use by Alaska Natives.
 </P>
<P>Because the CI beluga whale stock is depleted, any long-term,

Federally-approved management plan that includes harvest is

considered a major action subject to the requirements of the

National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA). NMFS is separately

preparing an Environmental Impact Statement (EIS) on conservation

actions that include proposed regulations to Federally regulate

the subsistence harvest of CI beluga whales by Alaska Natives

after 2002 and, thereby, to recover this stock. These
 
regulations and EIS will not be completed prior to the harvest in

2002, and therefore NMFS is completing an Environmental

Assessment (EA) on the harvest of [not to exceed] two whales for

this single season. The co-management agreement for 2002, and

supporting EA, are consistent with agreements and analyses that

were completed for previous single season harvests in 2000 and

2001. 
</P>
<P>NMFS evaluated the impact of allowing the harvest of two belugas

in 2002 using computer simulations. These simulations indicated
 
that the harvest of two belugas in 2002 would not significantly

delay recovery of the stock.
 </P>
<P>NMFS has determined that the harvest of two beluga whales during

the year 2002, as specified in the co-management agreement, will
 </P>
<P>not significantly impact the overall quality of the human

environment or cause any adverse impacts on species listed under

the Endangered Species Act (ESA). 
</P>
<P><StyleSpan>Summary of Environmental Impacts
 </StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>Alternative 1 (No Action) would result in the diminishment of

cultural values and traditional needs within the local CI native
 
community and the Native Village of Tyonek.
 </P>
<P>Alternative 2 would allow for the harvest of up to two whales

during 2002 from a stock which has been significantly exploited

in recent history, and which is now depleted. The level of
 
removal under this alternative would meet NMFS intent to provide

opportunity for continued traditional Native harvest while not

significantly extending time to recovery. The delay in recovery

time by selecting this alternative is negligible. This is the
 
alternative preferred by NMFS.
 </P>
<P><StyleSpan>Required Actions or Approvals
 </StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>NMFS would enter into a co-management agreement with CIMMC under

section 119 of the MMPA for 2002 under the preferred alternative.

A harvest of two whales would be authorized in this agreement

under the provisions of Public Law 106-553 for the year 2002.

Harvest in future years would be subject to Public Law 106-553

and Federal regulations under section 101(b) of the MMPA,

following the finalization of an EIS drafted by NMFS entitled


 , and subsequent promulgation of regulations.
 <StyleSpan>Federal Actions Associated With Management and Recovery of Cook

Inlet Beluga Whales</StyleSpan>
</P>
<Sect><Sect><P>The MMPA generally prohibits the taking, which includes

harassing, capturing, and killing, of marine mammals by U.S.

citizens or within the jurisdiction of the United States. The
 
MMPA imposes a general moratorium on the taking of marine

mammals. However, section 101(b) of the MMPA provides an

exemption from the take prohibitions by allowing Alaska Natives

to harvest marine mammals for subsistence use or for purposes of

traditional Native handicrafts. Under the MMPA, the Federal

Government may regulate this Native harvest if (1) the stock in

question is depleted, and (2) specific regulations are issued (16
</P>
<P>U.S.C.
 1371(b)). 
</P>
<P>The CI beluga whale stock was hunted by Alaska Natives, some of

whom reside in communities on or near CI and some of whom are
 
from other Alaska towns and villages. The whales concentrate off
 
the mouths of several rivers entering upper CI during the ice-

free season, making them especially vulnerable to hunting. Most
 
hunters used small motorboats launched from Anchorage to hunt

near these river mouths. The most common hunting technique was

to isolate a whale from a group and pursue it into shallow

waters. Whales were shot with high-powered rifles and may have

been harpooned to aid in retrieval. The muktuk (skin with some

of the underlying blubber attached), flippers, and tail flukes

were normally harvested for food, and some hunters also retained

the meat. 
</P>
<P>The CI stock of beluga whales is genetically and geographically

isolated from other Alaska populations of beluga whales. NMFS
 
has conducted annual surveys of the CI beluga whale since 1994.

Results of these surveys indicated that the CI beluga whale stock

declined by approximately 50 percent between 1994 (estimate of

653 whales) and 1998 (estimate of 347 whales). 
</P>
<P>The over harvest of beluga whales in CI for subsistence purposes

is believed to be the primary factor responsible for the decline.

Historically, harvest levels have been largely unreported.

However, during a study between 1995 and 1997, CIMMC estimated

that the annual harvest (including struck and lost whales) of CI

beluga whales averaged 77 whales per year. Harvest at these
 
rates could account for the 50 percent decline observed between

1994 and 1998. 
</P>
<P>Responding to the dramatic decline in this stock, NMFS initiated

a Status Review of the CI stock pursuant to the MMPA and ESA on

November 19, 1998. The CI beluga whales&#8217; present status and
 </P>
<P>health was reviewed and recommendations were accepted for

possible designation as depleted under the MMPA and/or listing as

endangered or threatened under the ESA. The comment period on

the status review (November 19, 1998 through January 19, 1999)

was initiated at the same time that workshops were being convened

to review beluga whale stocks throughout Alaska. The workshops

were held by the Alaska Beluga Whale Committee (ABWC) on November

16-17, 1998, and the Alaska Scientific Review Group on November

18-20, 1998, a body established under the MMPA to provide

scientific advice to NMFS regarding marine mammal conservation.

To further ensure the status review was comprehensive and based

on the best available scientific data, the closure of the public

comment period was followed by a NMFS-sponsored workshop that

reviewed relevant scientific information on this stock and
 
received additional public comments and recommendations on March

8-9, 1999, in Anchorage, Alaska. The proceedings and abstracts

of presentations from that workshop are summarized at Moore et.

al. (1999).
 </P>
<P>In January and March 1999, NMFS received petitions to list the CI

stock of beluga whale as &#8220;endangered&#8221; under the ESA of 1973, as

amended. NMFS determined that each of the petitions presented

substantial information which indicated the petitioned action may

be warranted (64 FR 17347, April 9, 1999). 
</P>
<P>At the time of the petitions, Federal regulations did not exist

to control the subsistence harvest, and cooperative management

agreements were not in place. To address this critical issue,

the following temporary moratorium was enacted (Pub. L. No. 106&#173;
31, &#167;3022, 113 Stat. 57, 100 (May 21, 1999)):
 </P>
<P>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the taking of a
</P>
<P>Cook Inlet beluga whale under the exemption provided in
</P>
<P>section 101(b) of the Marine Mammal Protection Act [16
</P>
<P>U.S.C.
 1371 (a)] between the date of the enactment of this

Act and October 1, 2000, shall be considered a violation of

such Act unless such taking occurs pursuant to a cooperative

agreement between the National Marine Fisheries Service and

affected Alaska Native organizations.
 </P>
<P>This moratorium was made permanent in December 2000 (Pub. L. No.

106-553, &#167;1(a)(2), 114 Stat. 2762 (December 21, 2000)).
 </P>
<P>Subsequent to the harvest prohibition, NMFS conducted a survey in

June 1999. The abundance estimate from this survey was 367

belugas. As a result of the abundance data and other information
 
presented in the status reviews, NMFS published a proposed rule

to designate the CI, Alaska stock of beluga whales as depleted

under the MMPA on October 19, 1999 (64 FR 56298). NMFS issued a
 </P>
<P>final rule designating the CI beluga whale stock as depleted on

May 31, 2000 (65 FR 34590). While the declining trend from 1994&#173;
1998 was significant, the 1999-2001 estimates of 367, 435 and 386

respectively, indicate that the population is apparently

increasing since harvest was restricted in 1999. The three
 
abundance estimates following the restriction of the harvest are

insufficient evidence for a conclusive evaluation of the
 
restriction; however, the apparent increase in the stock over the

1998 level is encouraging.
 </P>
<P>The 2002 agreement is presented in Appendix A. NMFS anticipates

developing similar agreement(s) to address the management of this

stock from 2003 to recovery.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>The purpose of this action is to enter into a co-management

agreement to authorize the taking of up to two CI beluga whales

in 2002 by Alaska Natives for traditional and cultural

subsistence purposes. This action is based on an analyses of

effects in a draft EIS on the long-term management and recovery

of CI beluga whales. This modeling analyses indicated that the

taking of up to two whales would not result in a delay of

recovery of beluga whales in Cook Inlet greater than 10 percent

of that which would occur without a subsistence harvest. NMFS
 
has found this level of effect negligible on the recovery of the

beluga whale population, and this level of take also provides for

the continuation of the subsistence harvest in Cook Inlet for
 
Native cultural and traditional purposes. Therefore, NMFS has

selected this alternative as the preferred alternative for this

action. Issues associated with this action include the impact of

the level of harvest and its effects on the recovery of this

stock, the impacts of not authorizing this harvest on Native

culture, and how Native subsistence harvest may be managed in the

future.
 </P>
<P>CIMMC is an organization comprised of Alaska Natives residing in

the CI region who share an interest in local marine mammals.

CIMMC includes CI tribes, Native hunters, and concerned Alaska

Natives. CIMMC was established to protect cultural traditions

and promote conservation, management, and utilization of CI

marine mammals by Alaska Natives. 
</P>
<P>The primary factor supporting this action is the need to

recognize the importance of the CI beluga whale to Native culture

and nutrition, and to provide for the continued opportunity to

harvest these whales within the recovery phase. The subsistence
 
harvest and use of the beluga whale is a component of Alaska

Native culture. The importance of the harvest transcends the
 </P>
<P>nutritional or economic value of the whale and provides identity

to the cultures which now harvest the whales. Native hunters
 
have stated their willingness to reduce harvest levels during the

recovery period, but also express their belief that the skills,

knowledge, and traditions associated with the subsistence hunting

of these whales cannot be passed on to younger generations unless

some level of harvest continues.
 </P>
<Sect><Sect><P>The principal objectives of this document are to assess the

consequences of entering into a co-management agreement allowing

two strikes on CI belugas during 2002 on the recovery of this

depleted stock to its Optimum Sustainable Population

 (OSP)

level, and to provide for the continued traditional subsistence

use by Alaska Natives to support their cultural needs. 
<StyleSpan>1</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>The NMFS/CIMMC agreement for 2002 represents a sharing of

responsibilities and is intended to provide for the necessary

authorities to manage this harvest, while allowing Alaska Natives

to manage many aspects of the hunt. The agreement will minimize

wasteful practices and improve the efficiency of the harvest.

All hunting parties must have a Native elder, experienced with

beluga hunting, present to direct the harvest. This will reduce
 
the chances of striking a calf, or female accompanied by a calf,

or of striking any whale in an area or manner that may result in

the loss of the whale. The agreement requires hunters to have

equipment necessary to recover and process the harvested whale.

All beluga hunting will be required to occur within the Susitna

River delta area to minimize disproportionate impacts to smaller

family groups. Hunting will be confined to certain time periods

to reduce the possibility of harvesting pregnant females. Taking

of calves, or adults accompanied by calves, will be prohibited.

The sale of edible portions will be prohibited. These, and

several other conditions to the hunt that have been agreed upon

and specified in the agreement, will greatly improve harvest

efficiency. Some of these requirements will be contained in

subsequent Federal regulations under the MMPA, while others will

remain the responsibility of the ANO. 
</P>
<P>Another provision of the agreement is the requirement for the

parties to consult whenever any unusual event has occurred which
 </P>
<P>
Optimum Sustainable Population is defined as the range of

population sizes between a stock&#8217;s carrying capacity and its

maximum net productivity level. 
<StyleSpan>1</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>might affect the impact of each year&#8217;s harvest on recovery, such

as a mass stranding or oil spill. The harvest would not proceed

after such an event until NMFS and the CIMMC had both given their

approval.
 </P>
<P>The environmental consequences section (Chapter 4) of the EA

discusses the impacts of a harvest of two whales (alternative 2)

as compared to alternative 1 which would result in a moratorium

on hunting CI beluga whales. Chapter 4 also reviews the socio&#173;
cultural impacts of the harvest on the traditional Alaska Native

cultures of CI. The alternatives are presented in Section 2.2.

The impacts of these alternatives are evaluated from information

and analyses presented in Chapters 3 (Affected Environment) and 4

(Environmental and Socio-cultural Consequences). This document
 
also addresses other issues that may impact beluga whales and

their habitat in CI. 
</P>
</Sect>
<Sect><Sect><P>NMFS would not enter into any cooperative agreements under the

provisions of Public Law 106-553 for the 2002 harvest under this

alternative. There would be no harvest authorized under this
 
alternative. This alternative would maximize the recovery

potential of the CI beluga whale stock.
 </P>
<P>2.2.2	 

CI beluga whales
 <StyleSpan>Alternative 2 - NMFS enters into an agreement with

CIMMC that provides up to two strikes of
</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>Alternative 2 establishes a harvest at two (2)strikes in 2002.

The goal of Alternative 2 is to allow the traditional subsistence

harvest of CI beluga whales by Alaska Natives to continue while

recovering this stock.
 </P>
<P>Subsistence hunting for CI beluga whales would only occur under

the terms of a co-management agreement (Appendix 1) under this

alternative. The terms of the agreement would (1) specify the

level of allowable take as two (2) strikes; (2) require all

hunting to occur after July 15, to minimize the harvest of

pregnant females; (3) prohibit the taking of calves or beluga

accompanied by a calf, and (4) provide other measures to improve

harvest efficiency. 
</P>
<P>This harvest would be administered jointly with Alaska Natives

through a cooperative agreement under section 119 of the MMPA.

The cooperative agreement would specify the level of harvest as
 </P>
<P>two (2) strikes. A strike would be considered any event in which

a bullet, harpoon, spear, or other device intended to take a

whale contacts a beluga whale. Multiple strikes on a single

whale would be considered one strike.
 </P>
<Sect><P>The purpose of this chapter is to describe the existing

environment, including conditions and trends, that may be

affected by the management alternatives. Because this assessment
 
focuses only on the development of a co-management agreement

between NMFS and CIMMC, and the biological and cultural

environment surrounding that activity, this section focuses only

on beluga whales and the use of beluga whales for subsistence

purposes. The reader may find a more detailed discussion of the

region&apos;s natural and human environments in the following

reference documents: NMFS&#8217;s 

, and MMS&#8217;s 

. 
<StyleSpan>Draft Federal Actions Associated with
 
Management and Recovery of Cook Inlet Beluga Whales Environmental

Impact Statement (2000)</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>Final Environmental Impact

Statement for the Cook Inlet Planning Area Oil and Gas Sale 149

(MMS 1996)</StyleSpan>
</P>
<Sect><P>Beluga whales are circumpolar in distribution and occur in

seasonally ice-covered arctic and sub-arctic waters. In Alaska,

beluga whales are found in marine waters from Yakutat to the

Alaska-Canada border in the Beaufort Sea. These comprise five

distinct stocks; Beaufort Sea, eastern Chukchi Sea, eastern

Bering Sea, Bristol Bay, and CI (Hill and DeMaster, 1998). Of
 
these, the CI stock is now considered to be the most isolated,

based on the degree of genetic differentiation between the CI

beluga whale stock and the four other stocks (O&#8217;Corry-Crowe et

al., 1997). The observed differences in mitochondrial DNA found
 
the CI stock was the most genetically distinct of the Alaska

beluga stocks, suggesting the Alaska Peninsula may be an

effective barrier to genetic exchange. Supporting this

assessment is the lack of observations of beluga whales along the

southern side of the Alaska Peninsula. Murray and Fay (1979)

postulated that this stock has been isolated for several thousand

years. 
</P>
<Sect><P>The beluga whale is a small, toothed whale in the family

Monodontidae, the only other member of which is the narwhal.

Beluga whales may reach lengths of 16 feet, although adult size

is more often 12-14 feet. Native hunters report some whales may

reach 20 feet. Males may weigh about 1,500 kg (3,307 pounds) and
 </P>
<P>females 1,360 kg (2,998 pounds) (Nowak, 1991). Beluga whales

lack a dorsal fin and do not typically produce a visible &#8220;blow&#8221;

on surfacing. Native hunters report these whales often surface

with only the blowhole out of the water. For these reasons, they

are often obscure and difficult to see from the water.
 </P>
<P>Beluga whales typically give birth to a single calf every two to

three years after a gestation period of approximately 14 months.

Calves are born dark gray to brownish gray and become lighter

with age. In CI, calving is assumed to occur from mid-May to

mid-July (Calkins, 1983), although Native hunters have observed

calving from April through August (Huntington, 1999). Alaska
 
Natives described calving areas within CI as the northern side of

Kachemak Bay in April and May, off the mouths of the Beluga and

Susitna Rivers in May and in Chickaloon Bay and Turnagain Arm

during the summer. The warmer waters from these freshwater
 
sources may be important to newborn calves during their first few

days of life (Katona, Rough, and Richardson, 1983; Caulkins,

1989). Adults are white to yellow-white upon sexual maturity,

although Burns and Seaman (1986) report females may retain some

gray coloration for as long as 21 years. Mating shortly follows

the calving period. Reports on the age of sexual maturity vary

from ten years for females and 15 for males (Suydam, Burns, and

Carroll, 1999), to four to seven years for females and eight to

nine years for males (Nowak, 1991). Beluga whales may live more

than 30 years (Burns and Seaman, 1986).
 </P>
<P>Beluga whales are covered with a thick layer of blubber, which

accounts for as much as 40 percent of its body mass (Sergeant and

Brodie, 1969). This fat provides thermal protection and stores

energy. Native hunters in CI report beluga whale blubber is

thinner in spring than late summer, suggesting that summer

feeding in the northern Inlet is important to the energetics of

these animals. NMFS has measured blubber thickness to be in
 
excess of 9 cm on CI beluga whales.
 </P>
<P>Beluga whales are extremely social animals which typically

migrate, hunt, and interact together. Nowak (1991) reports

average pod size as ten animals, although belugas may

occasionally form much larger groups, often during migrations.

Within CI, groups of 10 to more than 100 beluga whales are

typically observed during the summer. It is unclear whether
 
these represent distinct social divisions. Native hunters have
 
stated that beluga whales form family groups and that there are

four types of belugas in CI, distinguished by their size and

habits (Huntington, 1999).
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>Abundance surveys of CI beluga whales prior to 1994 were often

incomplete, highly variable, and involved non-systematic

observations or counts of concentrations in river mouths and
 
along the upper Inlet. Based on aerial surveys in 1963 and 1964,

Klinkhart (1966) estimated the stock at 300-400 animals, but the

methodology for the survey was not described. Sergeant and

Brodie (1975) presented an estimate for the CI stock as 150-300

animals, but offer no source for this figure. Murray and Fay

(1979) counted 150 beluga whales in the central Inlet on three

consecutive days in August 1978, and estimated the total

abundance would be at least three times that figure to account

for poor visibility. Calkins (1984) reported on surveys of the

upper Inlet between May and August of 1982, and estimated 200-300

belugas were seen in two concentration area. Hazard (1988)

stated that an estimate of 450 whales may be conservative because

much of CI was not surveyed in these efforts. 
</P>
<P>An aerial survey of CI in August 1979 resulted in a minimum

direct count of 479 beluga whales (Calkins 1989). Using a

correction factor of 2.7 developed for estimating submerged

whales under similar conditions in Bristol Bay, he estimated

maximum abundance of 1,293 whales. Because this is the most
 
complete survey of the Inlet prior to 1993, and because it

incorporated a correction factor for animals missed during the

survey in the abundance estimate, the Calkins summary provides

the best available data for estimating the historical abundance

of CI beluga whales.
 </P>
<P>NMFS began systematic aerial surveys of beluga whales in CI in

1994. Unlike previous efforts, these surveys included the upper,

middle, and lower Inlet. Using both observers and videotape,

this method also developed correction factors to account for

whales not observed due to coloration (calves and juveniles are

gray colored and do not contrast with the Inlet water), diving

patterns, or because whales were missed by the survey track.

These surveys have continued annually and have tracked a decline

in abundance of nearly 50 percent between 1994 and 1998.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>Beluga whales generally occur in shallow, coastal waters, often

in water barely deep enough to cover their bodies (Ridgway and

Harrison, 1981). Some beluga whale populations make seasonal

migrations, while others remain in relatively small areas year

round. It is presently unknown whether this stock migrates

seasonally from CI and, if so, where it goes. Sightings from

1976 to 1979, and in 1997; and satellite information on eight

tagged belugas from 2000-2002, indicate that at least some beluga

whales are present in CI year round, including the northernmost
 </P>
<P>reaches.
 </P>
<P>The whales return in large numbers to the upper Inlet in April

and May, commensurate with the eulachons&#8217; migrations to several

streams entering the northern portion of CI. It appears that a

relatively few discrete sites exist within upper CI which are

very important in terms of feeding habitat for the beluga whales.

Alaska Natives attribute this early movement into the upper Inlet

to whales following the whitefish migration (Huntington, 1999).

The beluga whales typically form several large groups during this

period and may reside in and near the Susitna River, the Little

Susitna River, and Turnagain Arm feeding on eulachon, salmon

smolt, and adult salmon. Beluga whales are known to migrate up

these river systems. Native hunters report belugas once reached

Beluga Lake from the Beluga River; and belugas are often seen

well upstream in the Kenai, Chickaloon, and Little Susitna

Rivers. By the end of June, the beluga whales disperse

throughout much of the upper Inlet. Important feeding and

concentration areas at this time expand to include Eagle River

estuary, Turnagain Arm, and Ship Creek. 
</P>
<P>A satellite tag was placed on a beluga whale captured near the

mouth of the Little Susitna River in late May of 1999. This
 
adult male was subsequently tracked over the next three months

until the signals from the tag ended on September 17, 1999. This
 
animal remained in the upper Inlet during this entire period, and

was observed within a large group of about 90-100 beluga whales

at the mouth of the Little Susitna River from late May to mid

June. The whale remained off the Susitna River and in Knik and
 
Turnagain Arms until the tag stopped transmitting. 
</P>
<P>Satellite tags were placed on two whales, a small female and

large male, captured on September 13, 2000. These whales were
 
tracked through January 2002, showing movements throughout the

upper Inlet, but rarely south of the Forelands. Calkins (1983)

postulated the whales leave the Inlet entirely, particularly

during heavy ice years. Surveys conducted by NMFS in November

and December 2000, along the upper Inlet observed no more than 20

beluga whales on any one day. Ten aerial surveys by Minerals

Management Service (MMS) between February 12 and March 14, 1997,

resulted in several beluga whale sightings in CI, no more than 40

belugas in a day. The actual number of animals represented by

these sightings is not reported. 
</P>
<P>In August 2001, satellite tags were place on six belugas, ranging

in size from 2.6 m - 4.4 m (8&apos;5&quot;-14&apos;6&quot;). These whales were
 
tracked throughout the fall and early winter, with one last tag

reporting on March 9, 2002, for a total of 202 days. For the
 
most part, all the six tagged whales remained in the icy upper
 </P>
<P>Inlet, rarely south of the Forelands. Monthly surveys conducted

by NMFS, from July through February, had raw counts of 204 to 0

belugas (in August and February, respectively).
 </P>
<P>Occasional winter sightings of beluga whales outside of CI (but

in the northern Gulf of Alaska) indicate that the CI stock may

not be confined to the Inlet. These sightings include sporadic

observations of beluga whales near Yakutat, 640 km southeast of
</P>
<P>CI. 
Twenty-one adult and five juvenile beluga whales were seen

near Yakutat in May of 1976 (Fiscus, Braham, and Mercer, 1976).

MMS (1999) winter surveys observed 10 beluga whales off Hubbard

Glacier near Yakutat, and the U.S. Coast Guard reported sighting

10 to 11 beluga whales there in November 1998. It is possible

these beluga whales are part of the CI stock. Consiglieri and

Braham (1982) reported annual observations of beluga in the

Yakutat area by local fishermen. However, Calkins (1986)found

these annual observations to be unsupported and believed the

Yakutat sightings were belugas from the CI stock. 
</P>
<P>Infrequent sightings have also occurred at Shelikof Strait,

Kodiak Island, Resurrection Bay and Prince William Sound.

However, sightings in all of these locations are rare or involved

relatively few animals. For example, a single beluga whale was

observed in Aialik Bay near Seward in 1988 (Morris, 1992).

Another single whale was reportedly seen near Montague Strait in

1978 (Harrison and Hall, 1978), in St. Matthew&#8217;s Bay in 1998 (D.

Janka, Pers. Comm.), and in Alitak Bay in 2001 (K. Wynne, Pers.

Com). The one exception is a report by Calkins (1986) of

approximately 200 beluga whales observed in July 1983 in western

Prince William Sound near Knight Island.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>Beluga whales are opportunistic feeders, and are known to prey on

a wide variety of animals. They eat octopus, squid, crabs,

shrimp, clams, mussels, snails, sandworms, and fish such as

capelin, cod, herring, smelt, flounder, sole, sculpin, lamprey,

and salmon (Perez, 1990; Haley, 1986; Klinkhart, 1966). CI
 
Natives also report that CI beluga whales feed on freshwater

fish; lingcod, trout, whitefish, northern pike, and grayling

(Huntington, 1999), and on tomcod during the spring (Fay et al.,

1984). Calkins (1989) reported recovering 13 fish tags from the

stomach of an adult beluga whale found dead in Turnagain Arm.

These salmon had been tagged in the Susitna River, as much as 80

miles upriver of CI. In captivity, beluga whales may consume

2.5-3 percent of their body weight daily, or 40-60 pounds. Wild
 
beluga populations, faced with an irregular supply of food, may

easily exceed these amounts while feeding on concentrations of

eulachon and salmon. CI beluga hunters report one whale having
 </P>
<P>nineteen adult king salmon in its stomach (Huntington, 1999). 
</P>
<P>The smelt-like eulachon (also named hooligan and candle fish) is

undoubtedly a very important food source for beluga whales in CI.

Eulachon may contain as much as 21% oil (total lipids) (Payne et

al., 1999). These fish enter the upper Inlet in May. Two major

spawning migrations of eulachon occur in the Susitna River, in

May and July. The early run is estimated at several hundred

thousand fish and the later run at several millions (Calkins,

1989). Stomachs of beluga whales harvested from the Susitna area

in spring have been filled with eulachon.
 </P>
<P>Salmon smolt are also an important prey item, as large numbers

leave these river systems in spring and summer and are available

to the belugas. Pink and chum salmon are most numerous during

June and July, and all five species of Pacific salmon are present

in the upper Inlet. Interestingly, a 1993 smolt survey of the

upper Inlet found juvenile herring the second-most abundant fish

species collected (Moulton, 1994).
 </P>
<P>Dense concentrations of prey appear essential to beluga feeding

behavior. Hazard (1988) reports belugas were more successful

feeding in rivers where prey were concentrated than in bays where

prey were dispersed. Frost et al. (1983) noted that beluga

whales in Bristol Bay feed at the mouth of the Snake River, where

salmon runs are smaller than in other rivers in Bristol Bay.

However, the mouth of the Snake River is shallower and, hence,

may concentrate the prey. 
</P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>Three sources of natural mortality are considered in this

section: strandings, predation, and disease.
 </P>
<Sect><P>CI. 
NMFS estimates over 600 beluga strandings (both individual

and mass strandings)in upper CI since 1988

. Mass strandings

have been most common along Turnagain Arm, often coinciding with

extreme tidal fluctuations (&#8220;spring tides&#8221;). These mass
 
strandings involve both adult and juvenile beluga whales. NMFS
 
has responded to such events since 1988, and although the

stranded animals usually swim away with the returning tide, some

mortalities have also been observed. A 1996 mass stranding of

approximately 60 beluga whales in Turnagain Arm resulted in the

death of four adult whales. Five adult beluga whales died from
 <StyleSpan>2</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>
This estimate includes 44 beluga whale carcasses found

along the shoreline which had been harvested for subsistence. 
<StyleSpan>2</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>another stranding of approximately 60 whales in August of 1999. 
</P>
<P>3.1.5.2 
Predation: The number of killer whales visiting

the upper Inlet appears to be small. However, they are known to

prey upon CI beluga whales. NMFS has received reports of killer

whales in Turnagain and Knik Arms, between Fire Island and

Tyonek, and near the mouth of the Susitna River. Native hunters
 
have recently reported killer whales along the tide rip that

extends from Fire Island to Tyonek (Huntington, 1999) and in

Kachemak Bay. 
</P>
<P>No quantitative data exist on the level of removals from this

population due to killer whale predation or its impact to the

beluga population. During a killer whale stranding in Turnagain

Arm, August 1993, a killer whale regurgitated a large piece of

beluga muktuk. In September 2000, a NMFS enforcement agent

witnessed at least three killer whales attack a beluga whale pod

in Turnagain Arm. Two lactating female beluga whaless later

stranded with lethal injuries consistent with a killer whale

attack. In October 2000, an eyewitness reported that at least

three killer whales attacked a juvenile beluga whale in the Kenai

River. A potential dietary shift may account for some of the

more recent sightings of killer whales in CI. 
</P>
<P>3.1.5.3 
Disease: Bacterial infection of the respiratory


st common diseases encountered in marine
 
mammals. Bacterial pneumonia, either alone or in conjunction

with parasitic infection, is a common cause of beach stranding

and death (Howard et al., 1983). From 1983 to 1990, 33 percent

of stranded beluga whales in the St. Lawrence estuary (n = 45

sampled) were affected by pneumonia (Martineau et al., 1994).

One beluga whale apparently died from the rupture of an &quot;aneurysm

of the pulmonary artery associated with verminous pneumonia&quot;

(Martineau et al., 1986). 
<StyleSpan>tract is one of the mo</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>Beluga whales appear relatively free of ectoparasites, although

both the whale louse, 

 sp., and acorn barnacles, 

, are recorded from stocks outside of Alaska (Klinkhart,

1966). Endoparasitic infestations are more common. An
 
acanthocephale, 

 sp., was identified in beluga whales,

and 

 has been found in Alaska beluga whales.


 is also recorded from belugas in eastern Canada

(Klinkhart, 1966). Results of necropsies from CI beluga whales

have found infestations in adult whales. Approximately 90

percent of CI beluga whales examined have had kidneys parasitized

by the nematode 

. This parasite occurs in

other cetaceans, such as Cuvier&#8217;s beaked whale, but has not been

extensively reported in other Alaska beluga stocks. Although

extensive damage and replacement to tissues has been associated
 <StyleSpan>Cyamus</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>Coronula
 
reginae</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>Coryosoma</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>Pharurus oserkaiae</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>Anisakis simplex</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>Crassicauda giliakiana</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>with this infection, it is unclear whether this results in

functional damage to the kidney (Burek 1999a). 
</P>
<P>Parasites of the stomach (most likely 

 or 

)

are often present in CI beluga whales. These infestations have
 
not, however, been considered to be extensive enough to have

caused clinical signs. Also recorded within muscle tissues of CI
 
beluga whales is 

 sp. The encysted (muscle) phase of

this organism is thought to be benign; however, acute infections

can result in tissue degeneration leading to lameness or death

(Burek, 1999b). 
<StyleSpan>Contracecum</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>Anisakis</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>Sarcocystis</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>The arctic form of 

 (a parasitic nematode) is

known to infect many northern species including polar bears,

walrus, and to a lesser extent ringed seal and beluga whales

(Rausch, 1970). The literature on &quot;arctic trichinosis&quot; is
 
dominated by reports of periodic outbreaks among Native people

(Margolis et al., 1979). The effect of the organism on the host

marine mammal is not known (Geraci and St. Aubin, 1987).


 has not been recorded within the CI stock of beluga

whales.
 <StyleSpan>Trichenella spiralis</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>Trichenella</StyleSpan>
</P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>Throughout the CI basin and specifically in Knik Arm and the

Kenai River, archeological research has found items both from the

Dena&#8217;ina Athabaskan and historic Eskimo cultures. The Pacific
 
Eskimos occupied CI as late as between A.D. 1000 - 1500

(Ackerman, 1975). The Dena&#8217;ina,

 also called the Tanaina, is one

of the Athabaskan peoples of Alaska that live in the CI region.

The Dena&#8217;ina moved to the CI area to escape the harsher extremes

of the interior (Chandonnet, 1985).
 <StyleSpan>3</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>Historically the Dena&#8217;ina Indians lived in an area that extended

around CI and inland, west to Iliamna Lake and Lake Clark, north

to the Devil&#8217;s Canyon in the Susitna River and the Matanuska

River drainage, east to the Kenai Mountains, and south to

Kachemak Bay. Unique among Alaska Athabaskan people, the

Dena&#8217;ina live along the Pacific Ocean and exploited the marine

resources, as well as lake, riverine, and interior environments. 
</P>
<P>
Russian scholars recorded the word Dena&#8217;ina with an initial
 
&#8220;t,&#8221; often spelling it &#8220;Tnana&#8221;. Cornelius Osgood used the

spelling &#8220;Tanaina&#8221; in his 1937 ethnology. The spelling Dena&#8217;ina
 
is the modern orthography (the apostrophe is the glottal stop).

This word means &#8216;the people&#8217; and is cognate with the Navajo term

dine&#8217; of the same meaning (Ackerman, 1975).
 <StyleSpan>3</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>The good climate and constant supply of adequate food made it

possible for the Dena&#8217;ina to live in semi-sedentary villages

throughout the CI region.
 </P>
<P>The Dena&#8217;ina seasonally crossed the Inlet in skin covered single-

or double-holed kayaks and the larger open boat, the badi, that

resembled the Eskimo umiak. In Knik and Turnagain Arms, with the

dangerous bore tides, the Dena&#8217;ina rarely traveled far by boat.

The Dena&#8217;ina originally learned how to make and use both types of

boats from their Eskimo neighbors (Ackerman, 1975). 
</P>
<P>CI offered a rich supply of marine resources such as beluga

whales, sea lions, seals, porpoise, and sea otter that fed on

salmon, eulachon, herring, cod, halibut, and shellfish. The
 
Dena&#8217;ina did not hunt the larger whales, as it was said that they

lacked the proper magic to kill them (Ackerman, 1975). Instead
 
this meat was obtained by trade. However, if they found a

beached whale, it was used. 
</P>
<Sect><P>Beluga whales provided meat and oil to the hunter&#8217;s family and

dogs. The meat was generally cut into strips and dried. The
 
blubber was rendered into oil and put into containers with lids

for the winter. Their sinews were made into ropes and string for

bow, because the beluga whale sinew string is strong (Pete,

1987). Their stomachs were used as oil containers. Beluga whale

(and bear) intestines were made into gut parkas for wet weather

gear (Ackerman, 1975). Beluga whales were an important food

source for the upper and outer Inlet Dena&#8217;ina, especially before

the moose arrived in the Inlet region in the late 1800&apos;s (Kari

and Kari, 1982). As important as the meat was, whale blubber and

oil were of even greater economic importance (Fitzhugh and

Crowell, 1988). 
</P>
<P>The blubber from beluga whales was rendered into oil to store

other foods or used in lamps for heat and light. Kalifornsky

(1991) reported that cooked clams were placed in a beluga whale

stomach and covered with oil to preserve the clams over the

winter. The clams were then washed in hot water and cooked
 
during the winter months. The beluga meat is eaten fresh, dried,

roasted, boiled, and ground. The skin and a layer of fat

(kimmuq, or muktuk) are eaten raw, pickled, canned, or boiled.

The ivory teeth are used in a variety of functions and were

important trade items (Fitzhugh and Crowell, 1988). Whale bone
 
was used in Native art (e.g., masks) and handicraft work.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>Inlet
 </P>
<P>The Susi Kaq &#8220;sand island mouth&#8221; (the Susitna Delta area,

including Big Island and the west channel of the lower

Susitna)(Pete 1987) was an important spring camping area on the

Inlet at the mouth of the Susitna River. Dena&#8217;ina gathered to

hunt beluga, ducks, and geese, to fish for salmon and eulachon,

and to trade.
 </P>
<P>Beluga whales were hunted between May and August at the mouths of

the rivers and streams (Pete, 1987). It required several hunters

to successfully harvest the beluga whale. The upper Inlet

Dena&#8217;ina method of catching the small white beluga seems to be

unique in North America, not borrowed from the Eskimo or Alutiiq

people (Pete, 1987). The Dena&#8217;ina used the tidal flats in the
 
Susitna Delta to hunt beluga whales. According to Pete&#8217;s (1987)

description, the hunters erected a yuyqul (beluga spearing

trees), which are dead spruce trees, root side up, in the mud

during a low tide. Each spruce tree had many ropes extending

from it and five or more people would pull on each rope to lift

the tree up. The sinew ropes were then secured to stakes. The
 
hunters climbed into the &#8220;nest&#8221; formed by the tree roots (Fall et
 
al., 1984) to wait for the beluga that would swim by with the

incoming tide. The hunters had harpoons fitted with a toggle

point and attached with braided sinew ropes (about 25 fathoms

long) to floats (usually inflated sealskin). Similar gear was

used to hunt Steller sea lions at Kachemak Bay. During the

incoming tide, beluga whales would chase the salmon and the

hunters would strike the beluga many times as it came by (Pete,

1987). The struck whales with the attached floats were pursued

by the hunters in boats until the whales tired and could be

killed by a hunter with a boneheaded spear. The whales were then
 
taken to shore and butchered. 
</P>
<P>With the introduction of firearms around the turn of the century,

the Dena&#8217;ina abandoned the yuyqul and weir methods for beluga

whale hunting, and used boats and firearms to shoot beluga whales

at the shallow river mouths. The three-man skin kayaks and

baidarkas were used on the Inlet, as late as the turn of this

century, to hunt seal, beluga whales, ducks and to collect clams

(Kalifornsky, 1991). 
</P>
<P>Beluga whales were hunted in Kachemak Bay, at Halibut Cove in the

1920&apos;s (Stanek, 1996). Hunters would line up along the point and

shoot the belugas and seals as they swam in with the tide. The
 
animals were retrieved from the lagoon where they floated, from

the beaches where they stranded, and from the shallow waters

where they sank. Kalifornsky (1991) reports that beluga whales

were regularly hunted at the mouth of the Kenai River before
 </P>
<P>1929.
 </P>
<P>Stanek (1996) reports that the residents of Tyonek historically

used another method to hunt beluga whales. A fence or weir was
 
constructed at the Beluga River and a movable dam made of poles

placed in &#8220;Takasitna Harbor,&#8221; which may have been Tuxedni Bay.

The beluga whales and seals chased the fish upstream with the

incoming tide. The movable poles were then placed to trap the

animals behind these structures with the outgoing tide and they

were then harvested.
 </P>
<P>Prior to the 1940&apos;s, beluga whales were a major part of Tyonek&#8217;s

diet, with Tyonek hunting six or seven whales annually in the

1930&apos;s and 1940&apos;s (Pete, 1987). Between the late 1940&apos;s and
 
1978, with a growing number of moose in the area, there was

little interest in beluga whales or any other marine mammal

hunting. However, since 1979, the beluga whale hunt has been

reestablished in Tyonek. The meat and blubber are shared
 
throughout the village (Fall et al., 1984).
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>In the late 1700&apos;s there were about 5,000 or more people around

the CI area (Ackerman, 1975). Today there are only about 1,000

people of Dena&#8217;ina ancestry living in the villages of Eklutna,

Knik, Kenai, Seldovia, Tyonek, Pedro Bay, Nondalton, Lime

Village, and Stony River, as well as in Anchorage. About 60
 
percent of Alaska&#8217;s population lives within the traditional lands

of the Dena&#8217;ina (Matanuska Valley, Anchorage Municipality, and

the Kenai Peninsula). In this dynamic region, about 30,000

people are Alaska Natives. 
</P>
<P>The CI marine mammal hunters who hunt beluga whales consist of
</P>
<P>Tyonek&#8217;s harvest of beluga whales has been modest; residents

there report about six to seven whales were taken annually during

the 1930&apos;s and 1940&apos;s, but very little beluga hunting occurred

between the 1940&apos;s and the late 1970&apos;s (Stanek, 1994). About
 
three beluga whales were taken in 1979, and one whale was

harvested annually between 1981 and 1983 (ADFG, undated).

Recently, Tyonek&#8217;s harvest has averaged one to two beluga whales

each year. The Beluga and Theodore Rivers are major hunting

areas for this village.
 </P>
<P>Beluga whales are now hunted with high-powered rifles from April

through October with most of the hunting between May and August

at the Susitna Delta area (Little Susitna River, west to the

Beluga River). Hunters use small motorboats launched from
 
Anchorage to access these camps and hunt in or near the river

mouths. Crews are often small, two to four persons, although

hunters may also hunt in groups. Kachemak Bay was usually hunted

in April and May, especially if the ice has not yet left the

upper Inlet. Knik Arm and Chickaloon River were occasionally

hunted in late summer and early fall, through October. The
 
hunters always collect the muktuk. Sometimes they collect the

meat and blubber for food, and bones and teeth for handicrafts.

The hunters wait at camp for the whales to enter shallow water or

chase whales already in the shallow waters. The dark, murky

waters of upper CI prevent detection of submerged whales, so the

hunters must follow the beluga whale&#8217;s &#8220;covenough,&#8221; or, wake,

that is created by the whale in shallow water. As the whale
 
breaches, the hunters generally shoot, then harpoon immediately

after, or harpoon first and then shoot. When the whale is dead,

the hunters attach a line through the lower mandible or around

its tail to tow it to shore.
 </P>
<P>The flippers and tail are considered a delicacy by some people,

and are generally removed first. The muktuk is taken from the
 
whale in large strips, about 24&quot; to 36&quot; in length and 18&apos; to 24&quot;

in width. The blubber is removed in square chunks. If any meat

is collected, it is the back strap and ribs. The remaining

skeleton, meat, and organs are often left on site, or if near a

village (like Tyonek), these parts may be used for dog food. In
 
Tyonek, the muktuk, blubber, and meat are shared throughout the

village. In Anchorage, portions are kept and shared with family

and friends. CI beluga whale parts have been sold in Anchorage

to Alaska Native food stores, sold within the Anchorage Native

community, and sold to Alaska Natives who live outside the

Anchorage area.
 </P>
<P>Reliance on whales as a primary food source diminished with the

rise of alternative means of subsistence, but the importance of

whaling in economic and cultural terms never disappeared
 </P>
<P>(Fitzhugh and Crowell, 1988). Alaska Natives continue to share
 
the meat and blubber in traditional patterns that reaffirm social

ties and provide a strong sense of ethnic identity (Fitzhugh and

Crowell, 1988). The use of beluga whales and other wild

resources continues to be economically, nutritionally, and

culturally valuable to the Dena&#8217;ina and other Alaska Natives in

the CI area. 
</P>
<P>The village of Tyonek has customary local rules which guide their

beluga hunters. These rules commonly guide aspects of the hunt

such as seasons, hunting areas, harvest methods, the social group

hunting, selection of types of animals, processing of animals,

uses of parts of the animals, and distribution of products. 
</P>
<P>A significant portion of the beluga whale hunters that currently

hunt within CI are not originally from the area, although they

hunted beluga whales in their villages and continued to hunt

belugas when they moved to the CI area (Anchorage, Matanuska

Valley, or Kenai Peninsula). There is some development of a

&#8220;community&#8221; from similar geographic areas, but most hunters are

independent. Other hunters, who are not local residents, but

regularly visit the CI area, hunt with family or friends in CI

where beluga whales are available all season
 </P>
<P>Historically, subsistence harvest levels of CI beluga whales have

been largely unreported. Estimated harvest for the years 1987&#173;
2001 are presented in the figure below. The sources of these
 
data include estimates by ADFG, reports from CIMMC, and data

compiled by NMFS based on reports from hunters and direct

observations of harvested whales. The large difference in the

number of beluga whales harvested before and after 1995 is due,

in large part, to improved efforts by the hunters in reporting

and the application of a correction factor for struck and lost

whales. No whales were reported harvested in 1999 and 2000, with

one beluga whale harvested in 2001 under a co-management

agreement. 
</P>
<P>The 1996-1998 estimates include animals struck, but lost, using a

ratio of one beluga whale lost for each landed. Struck and loss
 
estimates may be highly variable, although CIMMC (1997) reported

that this may be between one and two for each whale landed. Data
 
compiled by CIMMC for the 1995 harvest estimated strike and loss

at less than 1:1 (44 CI beluga whales were landed and 26 were

struck and lost) (CIMMC, 1996). NMFS estimated that the harvest
 
between 1995 and 1997 averaged 79 whales annually. At such a
 
level of harvest, this stock could be reduced by 50 percent of

its current level within five years. 
</P>
<P>It is not uncommon for beluga harvest efficiencies to be low. 
</P>
<P>Native hunters, themselves, reported an increase in the number of

struck and lost beluga whales, evidenced by whales observed

washed up on shore along the west side of the Inlet (Huntington,

1999). An efficient harvest in CI is confounded by the turbidity

of the water, large tidal fluctuations, mudflats, and currents.
 </P>
<Sect><P>This chapter evaluates the probable environmental, biological,

cultural, economic, and social consequences of the presented

alternatives. Generally, the direct biological consequences of

the alternatives concern the impacts of harvest on the recovery

of the CI beluga whales. Cultural and social impacts or

consequences would be realized within local Alaska Native

communities who are dependent on subsistence resources. There
 
are no apparent consequences of either of the alternatives on the

physical environment of CI, or on activities other than hunting,

that are ongoing in CI. Co-management of Alaska&#8217;s marine mammals

has generally proven to be very successful in allowing self-

determination among Alaska Natives in their subsistence harvest

practices while allowing for the necessary conservation of

important stocks. The endangered bowhead whale is harvested

under such an agreement between the Alaska Eskimo Whaling

Commission (AEWC) and National Oceanic and Atmospheric

Administration. Under that agreement, the bowhead whale has been

successfully harvested under the direction of the AEWC, and the

bowhead stock has increased steadily. The AEWC is responsible

for monitoring and reporting on the harvest, as well as enforcing

certain actions within their membership, while Federal authority

is retained.
 </P>
<Sect><P>NMFS evaluated the effects of the two harvest alternatives
 
presented in this assessment using a generalized logistics model.

Model parameters included the following: carrying capacity =

1,300, Maximum Net Productivity Level = 780, and Maximum Net

Productivity Rate = 4%. The starting population size was 386,

which was the estimated abundance in 2001. Using these

simulations, NMFS compared the time to recovery (abundance

greater than 780 whales) when no harvest was allowed and when the

harvest of two belugas were authorized in 2002. The time to
 
recovery without harvest was 22 years. The simulation in which
 
harvest was allowed also exceeded 780 whales in 22 years, and the

ending abundance level was about 1-2 whales lower when the 2002

harvest was included. Such a difference in results of these
 
simulations indicates that the results of the harvest would be
 
negligible on the CI beluga whale stock.
 </P>
<P>NMFS has used this simple logistic model to evaluate the impacts

of previous 1-year harvest agreements for 2000 and 2001 and to

evaluate the impacts of subsistence harvest on the recovery of CI

beluga whales. At a hearing related to the proposed rule to

regulate subsistence harvest of CI beluga whales, NMFS agreed

that the simple model was inadequate to incorporate the

considerable uncertainty related to many model parameters. Based
 
on evidence submitted at the hearing and stipulation of the

parties, the Administrative Law Judge found that the interim

harvest strategy of a total of 6 whales over the period 2001-2004

will not result in a significant retardation of the CI beluga

whale population and found that the best scientific evidence

available demonstrates that the interim harvest regime will not

significantly disadvantage the CI beluga whale population.

(McKenna, P.L. 2002. Recommended Decision in the matter of:

proposed regulation governing the taking of Cook Inlet, Alaska,

beluga whales by Alaska Natives. Docket number 000922272-0272&#173;
01, March 29, 2002).
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>NMFS would not enter into an agreement with an ANO under

Alternative 1. Therefore, under the requirements of Public Law

106-553, there could be no harvest on the CI stock of beluga

whales. This would result in a moratorium on the stock during

2002. Human-caused mortalities would be eliminated, or

significantly reduced, in 2002. The stock&#8217;s recovery would be

affected only by natural mortality.
 </P>
<Sect><P>Alternative 1 has few direct biological effects. A harvest would
 
not occur and whales would not be removed from this population by

hunting in 2002. Several indirect biological effects have been

identified as a possible result of selecting Alternative 1. The
 
lack of CI beluga whales taken in subsistence harvest by Alaska

Natives might place additional hunting pressure on other marine

mammal stocks in CI. Of these other marine mammals, only harbor

seals occur regularly in upper CI and an increased harvest of

this species for subsistence uses would be expected. Similarly,

there may be increased pressure on the harvest of beluga whales

from other stocks throughout Alaska. The stock considered most
 
likely as an alternative source of beluga whale muktuk for those

living in the CI region would be from Bristol Bay because of its

proximity and ease of shipping to Anchorage. The muktuk from one
 
beluga whale harvested in Bristol Bay was delivered to the

Anchorage Native community in 1999. This whale was incidentally

caught in a fishing net and was sent to an Anchorage hunter, who

then distributed it to Alaska Natives in both Tyonek and
 </P>
<P>Anchorage. In another instance, muktuk from a beluga whale taken

in October 1999 on the Naknek River was subsequently sold in

Anchorage. Some level of importation of beluga whale products

into the CI region may be expected. The four other Alaska beluga

stocks are currently healthy and could support an additional

small level of harvest. However, the subsistence use of these

stocks is managed through an agreement between NMFS and the ABWC

who would continue to address and manage any village concerns

associated with this trade. 
</P>
<P>An increased subsistence take of waterfowl and fish in the region

may occur without a CI beluga whale harvest. However, it is

difficult to predict whether or not there would be an increased

harvest of other subsistence species. Traditional Native foods
 
consist of a variety of things that are not necessarily

equivalent on a pound-for-pound basis (i.e, beluga whale muktuk

would not be replaced by a pound of fish or seal). Therefore,

there may be little interest among hunters in harvesting more of

these other resources than they currently do. Also, the amount

of these resources harvested is determined in part by their

availability, which is not expected to change. 
</P>
<P>Despite the loss of the opportunity to harvest beluga whales,

Alaska Natives would be expected to continue to utilize CI for

purposes of subsistence hunting, fishing, and gathering. These
 
activities may include large game hunting (moose and bear),

hunting of fur bearing animals, waterfowl hunting, marine mammal

hunting (mainly harbor seal), fishing for salmon and eulachon

(smelt), and plant and berry picking. The harvest and use of
 
these foods are activities with significant social and cultural

meaning as well as having economic importance. 
</P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>Alternative 1 could impact traditional Native culture in at least

two ways. Alaska Natives who have recently participated in the

hunting of CI beluga whales would not have the opportunity to

harvest this resource. Native hunters have expressed their

belief that traditional hunting skills and knowledge must be

passed on first-hand. Social standing within the Native

community is based, in part, on whaling activities. Whaling

captains, and those who secure and distribute Native foods, are

highly regarded. 
</P>
<P>Those hunters who have relied on beluga whales as part of their

annual Native food source, or for money through sale of edible

portions, would be adversely affected by this alternative. 
</P>
<P>The cultural aspects of this harvest may erode under this
 </P>
<P>alternative if it were implemented for an extended period of

time. However, it is doubtful that the traditional skills and

knowledge associated with this hunt would be lost based on the

one year implementation of this alternative. Nonetheless, it has

been emphasized to NMFS by Native hunters that without direct

experience in this harvest, these skills may not be taught and

passed on with the consequence being that the skill levels of the

hunters would eventually diminish.
 </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>NMFS would establish a harvest level of up to two (2) strikes for

the year 2002 under Alternative 2. The agreement authorized

under this alternative would expire at the end of 2002.
 </P>
<Sect><P>The direct biological consequence of this alternative would be

the removal of two (2) adult belugas from this population. With
 
this harvest, the impact would be negligible and would not delay

the rate at which the CI beluga whale stock would recover to OSP.

Therefore, the biological consequences would not be

distinguishable from the no-harvest regime in Alternative 1. 
</P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>A few Alaska Natives who have recently participated in the

hunting of CI beluga whales would have the opportunity to harvest

this resource, while additional Alaska Natives would benefit as

the beluga whale is shared under Alternative 2. Native hunters
 
have expressed their belief that the skills, cultural values, and

knowledge associated with this harvest must be passed on first&#173;
hand to younger generations, and that the tradition would die if

no hunting occurs for many years. 
</P>
<P>Those hunters who have relied on the harvest of beluga whales for

money would be adversely impacted by this alternative, as the

agreement prohibits such sales. The intent of this harvest is to
 
enrich and maintain the cultural tradition of hunting. The
 
traditional skills and knowledge associated with this hunt would

not be lost, and direct experience in this harvest would continue

to be taught and passed on. 
</P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>In its notice of determination concluding the status review of

Cook Inlet beluga whales under the ESA (65 FR 38778, June 22,
 </P>
<P>2000), NMFS analyzed factors that may be affecting the stock. In
 
that evaluation, NMFS stated that the subsistence harvest from

the early 1990&apos;s through 1998 could account for the observed

decline in the stock. NMFS also evaluated a wide range of human

activities and could find no evidence that suggested that these

activities, other than subsistence harvest, was having more than

a negligible impact on the stock. NMFS noted that the habitat
 
for beluga had been modified by municipal, industrial, and

recreational activities in Upper Cook Inlet but could find no

indication that human activities modified or curtailed the range

of Cook Inlet beluga to the extent that appreciably diminishes

the value of the habitat for both survival and recovery of the

species. The high levels of subsistence harvest that occurred

prior to 1999 have been eliminated, and the harvest of two whales

in 2002 would have a negligible impact on the stock.

Consequently, NMFS concludes that the cumulative impacts of this

harvest when added to the impacts of other activities within Cook

Inlet will be minimal.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>NMFS has determined that no species listed pursuant to the ESA,

or critical habitat, would be affected by this action.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>Implementation of the preferred alternative would be conducted in

a manner consistent, to the maximum extent practicable, with the

Alaska Coastal Management Program within the meaning of Section

307(c)(1) of the CZMA and its implementing regulations.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>The requirements for all regulatory actions specified in

Executive Order (E.O.) 12866 are summarized in the following

statement from the order: 
</P>
<P>In deciding whether and how to regulate, agencies

should assess all costs and benefits of available
 
regulatory alternatives, including the alternative of

not regulating. Costs and benefits shall be understood
 
to include both quantifiable measures (to the fullest

extent that these can be usefully estimated) and

qualitative measures of costs and benefits that are

difficult to quantify, but nevertheless essential to

consider. Further, in choosing among alternative

regulatory approaches, agencies should select those

approaches that maximize net benefits (including
 </P>
<P>potential economic, environmental, public health and

safety, and other advantages; distributive impacts; and

equity), unless a statute requires another regulatory

approach. 
</P>
<P>E.O.
 12866 requires that the Office of Management and Budget

review proposed regulatory programs that are considered to be

&quot;significant.&#8221; The proposed regulation is not considered a

&quot;significant regulatory action&quot; because it does not: (1) have an

annual effect on the economy of $100 million or more or adversely

affect in a material way the economy, a sector of the economy,

productivity, competition, jobs, the environment, public health

or safety, or State, local, or tribal governments or communities;
</P>
<P>The Regulatory Impact Review is also designed to provide

information to determine whether the proposed regulation is

likely to be &quot;economically significant.&quot; 
</P>
<P>This proposed regulation is not considered to have a significant

economic effect because it does not result in any of the impacts

described above. 
</P>
<Sect><P>No market exists wherein CI beluga whales are &#8220;traded&#8221; (in the

traditional economic sense). However, they have had economic

value to a few subsistence users. They also have had a large

cultural value to Alaska Natives, as well as a large non-

consumptive value to the non-Native public. In general, it can

be demonstrated that society places economic value on unique

environmental assets, even if those assets are never directly

exploited. That is, for example, society places real (and

measurable) economic value on simply &#8220;knowing&#8221; that, in this

case, CI beluga whales are flourishing in their natural

environment. 
</P>
<P>A substantial body of literature has developed which describes

the nature of these non- consumptive use values to society. In
 
fact, it has been demonstrated that these non-use economic values

may include several dimensions, among which are &#8220;existence&#8221;
 </P>
<P>value, &#8220;option&#8221; value, and &#8220;bequest&#8221; value. As the respective

terms suggest, society places an economic &#8220;value&#8221; on, in this

case, the continued existence of beluga whales in CI; society

further &#8220;values&#8221; the option it retains through the continued

existence of the resource for future access to the CI beluga

whale population; and society places &#8220;value&#8221; on providing future

generations the opportunity to enjoy and benefit from this

resource. These estimates are measures of the value society

places on these natural assets, and are typically calculated as

&#8220;willingness-to-pay&#8221; or &#8220;willingness-to-accept&#8221; compensation

(depending upon with whom the implicit ownership right resides)

for non-marginal changes in the status or condition of the asset

being valued.
 </P>
<P>Quantitatively measuring society&#8217;s non-consumptive use value for

an environmental asset (

.

., beluga whales), is a complex but

technically feasible task. However, in the current situation, an

empirical estimation of these values is unnecessary, because the

MMPA and the ESA implicitly assumes that society automatically

enjoys a &#8220;net benefit&#8221; from any action which protects marine

mammal species (including the habitat they rely upon), and/or

facilitates the recovery of populations of such species (or their

habitat). Therefore, it is neither necessary nor appropriate to

undertake the estimation of these benefits. It is sufficient to
 
point out that these very real &#8220;non-consumptive use&#8221; values to

society from conservation measures for CI beluga whales do exist.

Therefore, the effect of implementing the proposed action is

likely to produce an overall net social and economic benefit.
 <StyleSpan>e</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>g</StyleSpan>
</P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>The Regulatory Flexibility Act (RFA), first enacted in 1980, was

designed to place the burden on the government to review all

regulations to ensure that, while accomplishing their intended

purposes, they do not unduly inhibit the ability of small

entities to compete. The RFA recognizes that the size of a

business, unit of government, or nonprofit organization

frequently has a bearing on its ability to comply with a Federal

regulation. Major goals of the RFA are: (1) to increase agency

awareness and understanding of the impact of their regulations on

small business, (2) to require that agencies communicate and

explain their findings to the public, and (3) to encourage

agencies to use flexibility and to provide regulatory relief to

small entities. The RFA emphasizes predicting impacts on small

entities as a group distinct from other entities and on the

consideration of alternatives that may minimize the impacts while

still achieving the stated objective of the action. 
</P>
<P>On March 29, 1996, President Clinton signed the Small Business

Regulatory Enforcement Fairness Act. Among other things, the new

law amended the RFA to allow judicial review of an agency&#8217;s

compliance with the RFA. The 1996 amendments also updated the

requirements for a final regulatory flexibility analysis,

including a description of the steps an agency must take to

minimize the significant economic impact on small entities.

Finally, the 1996 amendments expanded the authority of the Chief

Counsel for Advocacy of the Small Business Administration (SBA)

to file amicus briefs in court proceedings involving an agency&#8217;s

violation of the RFA. 
</P>
<P>In determining the scope, or &#8216;universe&#8217;, of the entities to be

considered in an IRFA, NMFS generally includes only those

entities, both large 

 small, that can reasonably be expected

to be directly or indirectly affected by the proposed action. If
 
the effects of the rule fall primarily on a distinct segment, or

portion thereof, of the industry (

.

., user group, geographic

area), that segment would be considered the universe for the

purpose of this analysis. NMFS interprets the intent of the RFA

to address negative economic impacts, not beneficial impacts, and

thus such a focus exists in analyses that are designed to address

RFA compliance. 
<StyleSpan>and</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>e</StyleSpan>
<StyleSpan>g</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>NMFS has determined that this proposed rulemaking does not have

negative economic impacts to small entities as defined and, as

such, an Initial Regulatory Flexibility Analysis, pursuant to 5

USC 603, is not required.
 </P>
<Sect><P>This following groups or agencies have been consulted in the

preparation of this EA.
 </P>
<P>Cook Inlet Marine Mammal Council
 
Native Village of Tyonek

National Marine Mammal Laboratory

Alaska Beluga Whale Committee

Alaska Department of Fish and Game
</P>
<P>U.S.
 Army Corps of Engineers
 </P>
<P>The development of the agreement is the product of many

discussions, public meetings and coordination between NMFS and

CIMMC since the first public review of this issue which occurred

in Anchorage, Alaska, March 1999. The agreement had many drafts

and the final product is the result of review by CIMMC, and legal

counsel from both parties.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>NMFS proposes to enter into an agreement with an ANO authorizing

the take of up to two beluga whales during 2002. This
 
Environmental Assessment has been prepared to evaluate the

environmental impacts of this proposal and to provide sufficient

evidence to determine the level of significance of this action.

Based on this analyses, NMFS has determined that the harvest of

two belugas during the year 2002, as specified in the co-

management agreement, neither significantly impacts the overall

quality of the human environment nor causes any adverse impacts

on any species listed under the ESA or MMPA. Therefore, NMFS has

determined that preparation of an environmental impact statement

for the proposed action is not required by Section 102 (2) (C) of

NEPA or its implementing regulations.
 </P>
<P>Date
 
William T. Hogarth, Ph.D.

Assistant Administrator for Fisheries
 
National Marine Fisheries Service
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>P.
 Michael Payne

Assistant Regional Administrator

Protected Resources Division
 
Alaska Regional Office, NMFS

Juneau, Alaska
 </P>
<P>Brad Smith, Barbara Mahoney

Protected Resources Division
 
Alaska Regional Office, NMFS

Anchorage, Alaska
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>Ackerman, R.E. 1975. The Kenaitze people. Indian Tribal
 
Series, Phoenix, Arizona.
 </P>
<P>Burek, Kathy, D.V.M. 1999a. Biopsy report of beluga whale: Case

No. 98V0581. NMFS, Anchorage, Alaska. 3p.
 </P>
<P>Burek, Kathy, D.V.M. 1999b. Biopsy report of beluga whale: Case

No. 98V0579. NMFS, Anchorage, Alaska. 2p.
 </P>
<P>Burns, J.J., and G.A. Seaman. 1986. Investigations of belukha

whales in coastal waters of western and northern Alaska. II.
 
Biology and ecology. U.S. Dept. Commer., NOAA, OCSEAP Final

Rep. 56(1988): 221-357.
 </P>
<P>Calkins, Donald G. 1983. Susitna hydroelectric project phase II

annual report: big game studies. Vol. IX, belukha whale.

ADFG, Anchorage, Alaska. 15p.
 </P>
<P>Calkins, Donald G. 1984. Susitna hydroelectric project final

report: volume IX, beluga whale. ADFG Document No. 2328. 

17p. 
</P>
<P>Calkins, Donald G. 1986. Marine mammals. In: The Gulf of Alaska
 
physical environment and biological resources. D.W. Hood
 
and S.T. Zimmerman, eds. OCS study, MMS 86-0095. pp. 527&#173;</P>
<P>558.
 </P>
<P>Calkins, Donald G. 1989. Status of belukha whales in Cook
 
Inlet. In: Gulf of Alaska, Cook Inlet, and North Aleutian

Basin information update meeting. L.E. Jarvela and L.K.

Thorsteinson (Eds). Anchorage, Ak., Feb. 7-8, 1989.

Anchorage, Ak.: USDOC, NOAA, OCSEAP, pp. 109-112.
 </P>
<P>Chandonnet, A. 1985. On the trail of Eklutna. User Friendly

Press. Anchorage, Alaska.
 </P>
<P>Consiglieri, L.D., and H.W. Braham. 1982. Seasonal distribution
 
and relative abundance of marine mammals in the Gulf of
 
Alaska. Research Unit 68. NOAA, OCSEAP, Juneau. 212p.
 </P>
<P>Cook Inlet Marine Mammal Council. 1996. Native harvest and use
 
of beluga in the upper Cook Inlet from July 1 through

November 15, 1995. NMFS, Anchorage, Alaska. 3p.
 </P>
<P>Fall, J.A., D.J. Foster, and R.T. Stanek. 1984. The use of fish
 
and wildlife resources in Tyonek, Alaska. Alaska Department

of Fish and Game, Division of Subsistence. Technical Paper
 </P>
<P>Number 105.
 </P>
<P>Fay, J.A., D.J. Foster, and R.T. Stanek. 1984. The use of fish
 
and wildlife resources in Tyonek, Alaska. ADFG, Div.

Subsistence, Anchorage, Tech. Rep. Ser. 105. 219p.
 </P>
<P>Fay, Richard R. 1988. Hearing in vertebrates: a psychophysics

databook. Winnetka, Illinois: Hill-Fay Associates.
 </P>
<P>Fiscus, C.H., H.W. Braham, and R. W. Mercer. 1976. Seasonal
 
distribution and relative abundance of marine mammals i nthe
 
Gulf of Alaska. Proc. Rept. NMFS/NMML, Seattle, WA.
 </P>
<P>Fitzhugh, W.W. and A. Crowell. 1988. Crossroads of continents,

cultures or Siberia and Alaska. Smithsonian Institution
 
Press.
 </P>
<P>Frost, K.J., L.F. Lowry, and R.R. Nelson. 1983. Investigations

of belukha whales in coastal waters of western and northern
 
Alaska, 1982-1983: marking and tracking of whales in Bristol

Bay. U.S. Dept. Commer., NOAA, OCSEAP Final Rep.

43(1986):461-585.
 </P>
<P>Geraci, J.R. and D.J. St. Aubin. 1987. Effects of parasites on

marine mammals. International Journal for Parasitology

17(2):407-414.
 </P>
<P>Haley, Delphine. 1986. Marine Mammals. Second edition. Seattle:
 
Pacific Search Press. 
</P>
<P>Harrison, C.S. and J.D. Hall. 1978. Alaskan distribution of the
 
beluga whale, Delphinapterus leucas. Can. Field Nat. 92(3):

235-241.
 </P>
<P>Hazard, Katherine. 1988. Beluga whale, Delphinapterus leucas. 

In: Selected marine mammals of Alaska: species accounts with

research and management recommendations. J.W. Lentfer, ed.

Mar. Mammal Comm., Washington, D.C.
 </P>
<P>Hill, P.S., and D.P. DeMaster. 1998. Alaska marine mammal stock
 
assessments, 1998. U.S. Dep. Commer., NOAA Tech. Memo. NMFS&#173;
AFSC-97, 166p.
 </P>
<P>Howard, E.B., J.O. Britt, G.K. Marsumoto, R. Itahara, and C.N.

Nagano. 1983. Bacterial Diseases. Pp. 70-118 in: E.B.

Howard (ed.) Pathology of marine mammal diseases, Vol. 1.

CRC Press, Boca Raton, FL. 238p.
 </P>
<P>Huntington, Henry P. 1999. Traditional ecological knowledge of
 </P>
<P>beluga whales in Cook Inlet, Alaska. Report to the Alaska

Beluga Whale Committee and Cook Inlet Marine Mammal Council.

13p.
 </P>
<P>Kalifornsky, P. 1991. A Dena&#8217;ina Legacy (K&#8217;tl&#8217;egh&#8217;i sukdu), the

collected writings of Peter Kalifornsky. Edited by J. Kari

and A. Borass. Alaska Native Language Center. Fairbanks,

Alaska.
 </P>
<P>Kari, J. and P.R. Kari. 1982. Dena&#8217;ina Elnena, Tanaina Country.

Alaska Native Language Center, Univ. of Alaska, Anchorage,

AK.
 </P>
<P>Katona, Steven K., V. Rough, and D.T. Richardson. 1983. A field
 
guide to the whales, porpoises and seals of the Gulf of

Maine and eastern Canada. New York: Charles Scribner&apos;s
 
Sons. 
</P>
<P>Klinkhart, E.G. 1966. The beluga whale in Alaska. Alaska Dept.

Fish and Game. Fed. Aid in Wildlife Restoration Proj. Rep.

Vol. VII. 11p.
 </P>
<P>Margolis, H.S., J.P. Middaugh, and R.D. Burgess. 1979. Arctic
 
trichinosis: two Alaskan outbreaks from walrus meat. Journal
 
of Infectious Diseases 139:102-105.
 </P>
<P>Martineau, D., S. De Guise, M. Fournier, L. Shugart, C. Girard,
</P>
<P>A.
 Lagace, and P. Beland. 1994. Pathology and toxicology

of beluga whales from the St. Lawrence Estuary, Quebec,

Canada. Past, present and future. The Science of the Total

Environment 154:201-215.
 </P>
<P>Martineau, D., A. Lagace, P. Beland and C. Desjardins. 1986. 

Rupture of a dissecting aneurysm of the pulmonary trunk in a

beluga whale (Delphinapterus leucas). Journal of Wildlife

Disease 22(2):289-294.
 </P>
<P>Minerals Management Service. 1999. Distribution of Cook Inlet
 
beluga whales (Delphinapterus leucas) in winter. U.S. Dept.

Int. Alaska OCS Region. OCS Study MMS 99-0024. 30p.
 </P>
<P>Moore, Sue. E., D.J. Rugh, K.W. Shelden, and B.A. Mahoney. 1999. 

Beluga whale habitat in Cook Inlet, Alaska. Unpub. Report

National Marine Mammal Laboratory, NMFS., Seattle,

Washington.
 </P>
<P>Morris, Ronald J. 1992. Status report on Cook Inlet belugas

(Delphinapterus leucas). NOAA, NMFS. Anchorage, Alaska. 22p.
 </P>
<P>Moulton, Lawrence L. 1994. 1993 northern Cook Inlet smolt
 
studies. Draft report for ARCO Sunfish project. MJM

Research. 100p.
 </P>
<P>Murray, N.K., and F.H. Fay. 1979. The white whales or belukhas,

Delphinapterus leucas, of Cook Inlet, Alaska. Draft
 
prepared for June 1979 meeting of the Sub-committee on Small

Cetaceans of the Scientific Committee on Small Cetaceans of
 
the Scientific Committee of the Int&#8217;l Whaling Comm. College

of Environmental Sciences, Univ. Alaska, Fairbanks. 7pp.
 </P>
<P>National Marine Fisheries Service. 2000. Draft Federal Actions
 
Associated with Management and Recovery of Cook Inlet Beluga

Whales, Environmental Impact Statement, October 2000. U.S.
 
Dept of Commerce, NMFS, Alaska Region, Juneau, Alaska.
 </P>
<P>Nowak, Ronald M. 1991. Walker&#8217;s marine mammals of the world.
 
Volume 2. Fifth Ed. Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins University

Press.
 </P>
<P>O&#8217;Corry-Crowe, G.M., R.S. Suydam, A. Rosenberg, K.J. Frost, and
</P>
<P>A.E.
 Dizon. 1997. Phylogeography, population structure

and dispersal patterns of the beluga whale Delphinapterus

leucas in the western Nearctic revealed by mitochondrial

DNA. In: Molecular Ecology, Vol. 6: 955-970.
 </P>
<P>Payne, Susan A., B.A. Johnson, and R.S. Otto. 1999. Proximate
 
composition of some north-eastern Pacific forage fish

species. Fish Oceanogr. 8:3, 159-177.
 </P>
<P>Perez, Michael A. 1990. NOAA technical memorandum NMFS
 
F/NWC-186. Review of marine mammal population and prey

information for Bering Sea ecosystem studies. 
</P>
<P>Pete, S. 1987. Shem Pete&#8217;s Alaska, the Territory of the upper

Cook Inlet Dena&#8217;ina. Alaska Native Language Center,

University of Alaska, Anchorage, Alaska.
 </P>
<P>Rausch, R.L. 1970. Trichinosis in the Arctic. Pp. 348-373 in:
</P>
<P>S.E.
 Gould (ed.) Trichinosis in man and animals. Charles C.

Thomas, Springfield, IL.
 </P>
<P>Ridgway, Sam and Sir Richard Harrison. 1981. Eds., Handbook of

marine mammals. Volume 4. London: Academic Press. 
</P>
<P>Sergeant, D.E. and P.F. Brodie. 1969. Body size in white

whales, Delphinapterus leucas. Journal Fisheries Research
 
Board of Canada 26(10), pp. 2561-2580. 
</P>
<P>Sergeant, D.E. and P.F. Brodie. 1975 Identity, abundance, and

present status of white whales, Delphinapterus leucas, in
 
north America. Journal Fisheries Research Board of Canada
 
32(7), 1975, pp. 1047-1054. 
</P>
<P>Stanek, Ronald T. 1996. Belukha hunters of Cook Inlet, Alaska.

In Adventures through time: readings in the anthropology of

Cook Inlet, Alaska. Edited by N. Yaw Davis and W.E. Davis.

The Cook Inlet Historical Society, Inc. Anchorage, Alaska.
 </P>
<P>Suydam, Robert, J.J. Burns, and G. Carroll. 1999. Age, growth,

and reproduction of beluga whales from the eastern Chukchi

Sea, Alaska. Paper presented to the Alaska Beluga Whale

Committee workshop, March 30-April 1, 1999. 5 pp.
 </P>
<P>9.0	 
Appendix I: AGREEMENT between the NATIONAL MARINE FISHERIES

SERVICE and the COOK INLET MARINE MAMMAL COUNCIL for the CO&#173;
MANAGEMENT OF THE COOK INLET STOCK OF BELUGA WHALE for the 

YEAR 2002
 </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>This document constitutes an agreement between the National

Marine Fisheries Service (NMFS) and the Cook Inlet Marine

Mammal Council (CIMMC), otherwise referred to as the

Parties.
 </P>
<P>CIMMC is an association, chartered by the Cook Inlet Treaty

Tribes, which represents these Tribes and Alaska Native

marine mammal subsistence hunters within the Cook Inlet area
 
who are registered with CIMMC. 
</P>
<P>The Cook Inlet (CI) stock of beluga whales applies to

all beluga whales occurring in waters of the Gulf of

Alaska north of 58 degrees North latitude including but

not limited to, Cook Inlet, Kamishak Bay, Chinitna Bay,

Tuxedni Bay, Prince William Sound, Yakutat Bay,

Shelikof Strait, and off Kodiak Island and freshwater

tributaries to those waters.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>(I)	 
NMFS has the authority to enter into this agreement

with CIMMC under section 119 (16 U.S.C. 1388) of the

Marine Mammal Protection Act of 1972 (MMPA). Section
 
3022 of the 1999 Emergency Supplemental Appropriations

Act (Pub. L. 106-31) provided a temporary requirement

that the hunting of Cook Inlet beluga whales for

subsistence uses by Alaska Natives must be conducted

pursuant to a cooperative agreement between NMFS and

affected Alaska Native organizations; this requirement

for a cooperative agreement was subsequently made

permanent by section 627 of Pub. L. 106-553.

Additional guidance is provided by Executive Order

#13084 of May 14, 1998 (&#8220;Consultation and Coordination

with Indian Tribal Governments,&#8221; 63 FR 27655),

Presidential Memorandum of April 29, 1994 &#8220;Government&#173;
to-Government Relations with Native American Tribal
 
Governments,&#8221; U.S. Department of Commerce Memorandum

&#8220;American Indian and Alaska Native Policy of the U.S.
 </P>
<P>Department of Commerce&#8221; of March 30, 1995, and the

&#8220;Memorandum of Agreement for Negotiation of Marine

Mammal Protection Act, section 119 Agreements&#8221; of

August 1997.
 </P>
<P>B.	 
CIMMC has the authority to enter into this agreement

under its charter and authorizing resolutions from

Alaska tribal governments. Further, CIMMC is

recognized as an Alaska Native organization under the

MMPA and, as such, may enter into this agreement to co-

manage the subsistence use of marine mammals by Alaska

Natives. 
</P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>The purposes of this agreement between NMFS and CIMMC are to

promote the recovery of the CI stock of beluga whales; to

meet the subsistence needs and customs, traditions, and

culture of Alaska Natives by providing an opportunity for a

limited harvest of the CI beluga whale by the Native Village

of Tyonek (NVT) and the Alaska Native Marine Mammal Hunters

Committee (ANMMHC) during 2002; and to promote scientific

research on the CI beluga whale stock and their habitat.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>In 1972, the MMPA was passed by Congress and provided an

exemption which allows the taking of marine mammals by

Alaska Natives provided such taking is for subsistence

purposes or done for purposes of creating and selling

authentic Native articles of handicraft and clothing. Such
 
taking may not be accomplished in a wasteful manner. 
</P>
<P>In 1994, CIMMC was established to facilitate cooperation and

communication among beluga whale subsistence hunters,

scientists, and the government regarding the conservation

and management of CI beluga whales. CIMMC is composed of

Cook Inlet village representatives and hunters who hunt CI

beluga whales.
 </P>
<P>In April 1994, the MMPA was amended to include section 119

&quot;Marine Mammal Cooperative Agreements in Alaska.&quot; Section
 
119 formalizes the rights of Alaska Native organizations to

participate in conservation-related co-management of

subsistence resources and their use. Section 119 also
 
authorized the appropriation of funds to be transferred by

NMFS to Alaska Native organizations to accomplish these
 </P>
<P>activities. 
</P>
<P>On May 21, 1999, Pub. L. 106-31 required that the taking of

a CI beluga whale shall occur pursuant to a cooperative

agreement between NMFS and affected Alaska Native

organizations. This authority expired on October 1, 2000.
 </P>
<P>On December 21, 2000, the requirement, established in May

1999, for a cooperative agreement was made permanent.
 </P>
<Sect><P>The Parties agree that the Native harvest of CI beluga

whales during the calendar year 2002 shall consist of two
</P>
<P>(2)
 strikes. CIMMC shall allocate one strike to NVT and the
 
second strike to the ANMMHC. A strike is defined as hitting

a whale with a harpoon, lance, bullet or other object. Upon

striking a whale, subsequent strikes on that same whale are

not counted against the strike limit. 
</P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>5
 </P>
<P>CIMMC and ANMMHC shall notify NMFS Enforcement,

Anchorage office, 48 hours prior to the hunt. 
</P>
<P>consistent with the primary goals of the

parties as set forth in Section III of

this agreement. NMFS may suspend

further hunting at any time if it finds

unanticipated deaths within this stock

are too high to permit additional

removals consistent with recovery of the

CI beluga.
 </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>1.1 	
CIMMC, in cooperation with NMFS, will manage the CI

beluga whale subsistence harvest. The authority and

responsibilities of CIMMC are specified by this

agreement. CIMMC may provide for monitors to be aboard

the whaling vessel to verify and report on the strike.
 </P>
<P>1.2 	
CIMMC and NMFS shall communicate on an as-needed basis
 
concerning matters related to the enforcement of this

agreement or the Harvest Permit. Any party to this

agreement which initiates an enforcement action for a

violation of a prohibition involving Native take of the

CI whale shall notify, as soon as practical, the other

party to this agreement of the enforcement action.
 </P>
<P>C. 	
CIMMC, in consultation with NMFS, may conduct research

on the biology, natural history and traditional

knowledge of the CI population of beluga whales. NMFS
 
personnel may participate in such data collection.

All information collected under this section shall be
 
shared between CIMMC and NMFS.
 </P>
<P>D. 	
No financial commitment on the part of CIMMC is

authorized or required by this agreement.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>A.	 
NMFS has primary responsibility within the United

States Government for the management of beluga whales.

NMFS may assert its Federal authority to enforce any

provisions of the MMPA that are applicable to the

Native harvest of beluga whales. Such assertion of
 
Federal authority will be preceded by consultation with

CIMMC as specified in VII.B. below. 
</P>
<P>1.2 	
NMFS and CIMMC shall communicate on an as-needed basis
 
concerning matters related to the enforcement of this

agreement or the Harvest Permit. Any party to this

agreement which initiates an enforcement action for a

violation of a prohibition involving Native take of the

CI whale shall notify, as soon as practical, the other

party to this agreement of the enforcement action.
 </P>
<P>1.3 	
NMFS, in consultation with CIMMC, may conduct research

on the biology, natural history and traditional

knowledge of the CI population of beluga whales. CIMMC
 
personnel may participate in such data collection. All
 
information collected under this section shall be
 
shared between CIMMC and NMFS.
 </P>
<P>1.4 	
No financial commitment on the part of NMFS is

authorized or required by this agreement.
 </P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>NMFS recognizes the existing tribal authority to regulate

tribal members during the conduct of the subsistence harvest

of beluga whales. CIMMC recognizes the Secretary of

Commerce&apos;s authority to enforce the provisions of the MMPA

applicable to the Native harvest of beluga whales. 
</P>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>A.	 
Nothing herein is intended to conflict with current

NOAA or NMFS directives. If the terms of this
 
agreement are inconsistent with existing laws,

regulations, or directives of either of the Parties,

then those portions which are determined to be

inconsistent shall be invalid, but the remaining terms

and conditions not affected by the inconsistency shall

remain in full force and effect. At the first
 
opportunity for review of the agreement, all necessary

changes will be accomplished by either an amendment to

this agreement or by a new agreement, whichever is

deemed expedient to the interest of both Parties. 
</P>
<P>B.	 
Should disagreements arise over the provisions of this

agreement, or amendments or revisions thereto, that

cannot be resolved at the operating level, the area(s)

of disagreement shall be stated in writing by each

Party and presented to the other Party for
 </P>
<P>consideration. If agreement on interpretation cannot

be reached within a reasonable time, a special meeting

or teleconference shall be held to resolve the issues. 

This meeting shall include representatives of NMFS and

CIMMC. 
</P>
<Sect><P>This agreement will become effective when signed by both

Parties, may be amended at any time by written agreement of

both Parties, and shall expire on December 31, 2002. Either
 
Party may terminate this agreement by giving 45 days prior

written Notice of Termination to the other Party.
 </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
<Sect><P>The Parties hereto have executed this agreement as of the
</P>
<P>last written date below:
 </P>
<P>Peter Merryman Date 

Chairman, Cook Inlet Administrator, Alaska Region

Marine Mammal Council National Marine Fisheries Service
 
PO Box 82009 Juneau, Alaska 99802

Tyonek, AK 99682
 <StyleSpan>James W. Balsiger Date
 </StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>Agreement between the Cook Inlet Marine Mammal Council and the

National Marine Fisheries Service Entered into Pursuant to
 
Section 119 of the Marine Mammal Protection Act of 1972, As

Amended.
 </P>
<P>Appendix
 </P>
<P>List of Tribally-authorized Organizations Providing Authorizing

Resolutions to the Cook Inlet Marine Mammal Council. This list
 
may be amended from time to time if additional authorizing

resolutions are received from tribally authorized organizations

representing CI beluga whale hunters, and with CIMMC approval.
 </P>
<P><StyleSpan>Tribally Authorized Organization Resolution Date 
</StyleSpan>
</P>
<P>Cook Inlet Treat Tribes
 
Kenaitze Indian Tribe
 
Knik Tribe
 
Native Village of Chickaloon 

Native Village of Eklutna
 
Native Village of Tyonek
 
Ninilchik Traditional Council
 
Qutekcok Native Tribe
 
Seldovia Village Tribe
 </P>
</Sect>
</Part>
